<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Using the Product Servlet</title>
    <author email="kelly@apache.org">Sean Kelly</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Using the Product Servlet">
      <p>The query servlet is nice for general purpose queries, but for
	those who just want to retrieve products, it's a bit annoying to
	have to process all that XML and do base-64 conversions.  Is there
	a simpler way?  Absolutely.  The product servlet deals with just
	products, and delivers them in their appropriate form direct over
	HTTP.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Requirements">

      <p>The product servlet provides HTTP access to products, so
	naturally, you'll need to use a language or system that supports
	HTTP client access to HTTP servers.  Where can you find such a
	system?  Your handy-dandy web browser is one!  Most programming
	languages also have HTTP APIs either built-in or freely available.
      </p>

      <p>You also need to know</p>

      <ul>
	<li>The URL of the product servlet that has access to the
	  product server you want to query.</li>
	<li>The object name of the product server you want to
	  access.</li>
	<li>The keyword query expression that can be understood by the
	  product server.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Making a Query">

      <p>The product servlet accepts either <code>GET</code> or
	<code>POST</code> requests of URL-encoded form data.  In
	response, it delivers a matching product (if any can be found)
	in the format appropriate to the product's MIME type.  You can
	also request a specific MIME type.  If there's no matching
	product, you get HTTP error 404 (not found).
      </p>

      <p>The parameters that the servlet expects are:</p>

      <table border="0" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0">

	<thead>
	  <tr>
	    <th>Parameter Name</th>
	    <th>Obligation</th>
	    <th>Meaning</th>
	  </tr>
	</thead>

	<tbody>
	  <tr>
	    <td><code>object</code></td>
	    <td>Once</td>
	    <td>Names the product server to receive the query.  This
	      parameter must be specified exactly once and takes the form
	      <code>urn:eda:<var>proto</var>:<var>name</var></code>, such
	      as <code>urn:eda:rmi:PDS.Atmos.Product</code> for the
	      RMI-accessed Atmoshpheres node of the Planetary Data System.
	    </td>

	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td><code>keywordQuery</code></td>
	    <td>Once</td>
	    <td>Lists the keyword query expression to pass to the
	      product server, such as <code>PatientID = 19928</code> or
	      <code>ONLINE_FILE_SPECIFICATION_NAME =
		data/images/mars.jpg</code>.
	    </td>

	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td><code>id</code></td>
	    <td>None or Once</td>
	    <td>Optional parameter that identifies a single product to
	      retrieve if more than one product match.  A product server
	      may return multiple matching products.  By default, the
	      product servlet returns the first matching product only.  By
	      specifying the <code>id</code> parameter, you can select a
	      specific product when more than one match.  (In practice,
	      not a single product server <em>to date</em> has ever
	      returned more than one match.)
	    </td>

	  </tr>

	  <tr>
	    <td><code>mimeType</code></td>
	    <td>Zero to Many</td>
	    <td>Optional parameter that lists acceptable MIME types for
	      the product (see below).
	    </td>

	  </tr>

	</tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section name="MIME Types">

      <p>Many product servers are capable of conversion of products from
	a system-specific storage medium into an Internet-standard
	interoperable format.  Internet-standard MIME types are what
	drives this mechanism.  The product servlet can take a list of
	specific MIME types and pass them to the product server for
	consideration in retrieving your products.
      </p>

      <p>MIME type conversions are like <em>suggestions</em> to product
	servers.  Product servers are not obligated to honor all
	conversions, and indeed you may well receive 404 (not found) for a
	conversion that makes no sense to a particular product server
	(such as an audio clip to <code>text/html</code>).
      </p>

      <p>The <code>mimeType</code> parameter is what drives this
	mechanism.  By specifying one or more <code>mimeType</code>
	parameters in your <code>GET</code> or <code>POST</code> request,
	you list the preferred MIME types in which you would like the
	product delivered.  Furthermore, you can use wildcards to further
	enable a product server to satisfy you.  The ordering of the
	parameters is significant.
      </p>

      <p>Here are some examples.  Suppose the request URI part of the
	URL contained:</p>

      <pre>...mimeType=text/rtf&amp;mimeType=text/*...</pre>

      <p>This specifies two MIME types:</p>

      <ol>
	<li><code>text/rtf</code>, the Rich Text Format, is the
	  preferred format for delivering products.
	</li>

	<li><code>text/*</code> means any text type.  Any text is better
	  than no text if for some reason the product server can't give a
	  Rich Text Format product.
	</li>
      </ol>

      <p>Here's another example:</p>

      <pre>...mimeType=image/png&amp;mimeType=image/jpeg...</pre>

      <p>This indicates that you'd like a Portable Network Graphic
	format image, if possible, but will settle for a JPEG-JFIF format
	image.  No other image format (especially not the proprietary and
	ancient GIF format) is acceptable.  Adding an additional
	<code>&amp;mimeType=image/*</code> would mean any image format
	would be fine.  Adding <code>&amp;mimeType=*/*</code> means
	<em>any format</em> would be acceptable, be it audio, video, text,
	image, or otherwise.
      </p>

      <p>If there are <em>no</em> <code>mimeType</code> parameters, then
	the product servlet uses a default list containing just
	<code>*/*</code>, meaning any type is fine.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Example">

      <p>To retrieve an image of Mars from the PDS product server at the
	Imaging Node, in PNG format if possible and any image format
	otherwise, try the following:
      </p>

      <p><code><a
	    href="http://starbrite.jpl.nasa.gov/prod?mimeType=image/png&amp;mimeType=image/*&amp;object=urn:eda:rmi:PDS.Img.Product&amp;keywordQuery=ONLINE_FILE_SPECIFICATION_NAME+%3D+thumbnail/mgs-m-moc-na_wa-2-sdp-l0-v1.0/mgsc_1082/m09063/m0906352.imq.jpg">http://starbrite.jpl.nasa.gov/prod?<br/>mimeType=image/png&amp;<br/>mimeType=image/*&amp;<br/>object=urn:eda:rmi:PDS.Img.Product&amp;<br/>keywordQuery=OFSN+%3D+thumbnail/mgs-m-moc-na_wa-2-sdp-l0-v1.0/mgsc_1082/m09063/m0906352.imq.jpg</a></code></p>

      <p>This URL contains linebreaks for readability only.  Let's take
	this URL apart to see what's going on:
      </p>

      <ul>
	<li>The URL to the product servlet in this case is
	  <code>http://starbrite.jpl.nasa.gov/prod</code>.  Often the URL
	  will take this form, or may be
	  <code>http://<var>hostname</var>/servlet/jpl.oodt.servlets.ProductServlet</code>.
	  Most people prefer the shorter form.
	</li>

	<li>The question mark <code>?</code> separates the request URI
	  from its parameters.
	</li>

	<li>The first parameter, <code>mimeType=image/png</code>, says
	  that Portable Network Graphics images are preferred.
	</li>

	<li>The second parameter, <code>mimeType=image/*</code>, says
	  that if the product server can't convert to or other provide
	  Portable Network Graphics format images, then <em>any image
	    format</em> is acceptable.
	</li>

	<li>The third parameter,
	  <code>object=urn:eda:rmi:PDS.Img.Product</code>, identifies the
	  product server.
	</li>

	<li>The fourth parameter, <code>keywordQuery=...</code> names
	  the query expression.  In this case, it's <code>OFSN =
	    thumbnail/mgs-m-moc-na_wa-2-sdp-l0-v1.0/mgsc_1082/m09063/m0906352.imq.jpg</code>.
	</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The response to this URL's GET request is a JPEG-JFIF image
	(sorry, PNG's not yet available from the PDS Image Node)
	containing a picture of some planetary surface.  Neat, huh?
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
