<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Your First Product Service</title>
    <author email="Sean.Kelly@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Kelly</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Your First Product Service">
      <p>This tutorial introduces starting a basic product server.
	This product server will be capable of accepting queries, but
	will not actually respond with any data.  By completing this
	tutorial, you'll have a working product server in which you
	can install more complex logic to actually handle product
	requests.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="The Product Service">
      <p>The OODT Product Service is a remotely accessible software
	component that enables you to retrieve products, which can be
	any kind of data.  In OODT, a <em>product client</em> passes a
	<em>query</em> into a known product server.  The product
	server delegates that query to its installed <em>query
	handlers</em>; each one gets a chance at satisfying the query
	with requested data.  Query handlers are the interfaces between
	the generic OODT framework and your system-specific data
	stores.  They have the job of understanding the passed in
	query, finding or even synthesizing the matching product,
	applying conversions to Internet-standard formats, and
	returning results.  The product service then collects all the
	matching products from the query handlers and returns them to
	the product client.
      </p>

      <p>To deploy a product server, you need to come up with query
	handlers that interface to your site- or discipline-specific
	data stores.  Then, start a product server and inform it of
	what query handlers to use.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Delegation Model">
	<p>The OODT product service <em>delegates</em> incoming
	  queries to zero or more query handlers.  In the case of zero
	  query handlers, the product service always replies to every
	  query with "zero matches."  Otherwise, the query handlers
	  get a chance to satisfy the query, and may or may not add
	  matching products to the result.
	</p>

	<p>The following class diagram demonstrates this delegation model:</p>

	<img src="../../images/delegation.png" alt="Delegation Class Diagram" />

	<p>Here, a product client calls a server to process a query
	  for products. The server delegates to query handlers, which
	  are Java objects that implement the
	  <code>QueryHandler</code> interface.  Two query handlers in
	  this diagram, <code>MyHandler</code> and
	  <code>MyOtherHandler</code> can both try to satisfy the
	  query by adding matching products to the total result.  They
	  can each add more than one matching product, just one, or
	  none at all.  The server then returns the matches, if any,
	  to the client.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Large Products">
	<p>In OODT, a query contains its matching products.  When a
	  client passes a query to a product server, the query object
	  returns to the client <em>with matching products embedded in
	    it</em>.  This can, however, make query objects too large to
	  be comfortably passed around a network of OODT services (query
	  objects must reside completely in memory).  In this case, a
	  special extension of a <code>QueryHandler</code>, a
	  <code>LargeProductQueryHandler</code>, can instead place a
	  <em>reference</em> to the product data in the query.
	</p>
	<p>To product clients, the difference is invisible: the
	  product data is still accessed from the query object the
	  same way.  As a developer of product services, though, you
	  may need to decide which kind of query handler to make:
	  regular or large.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Communicating with a Product Service">
	<p>The product service is a remotely accessible object.
	  Therefore, product clients access it with a remote object
	  access protocol.  Currently, OODT supports RMI and CORBA.  You
	  can also access product services with HTTP; in this case, a
	  proxy object provides the HTTP interface while internally it
	  accesses a product service with RMI or CORBA.
	</p>

	<p>For this tutorial, we'll use RMI because it's enormously
	  less complex than CORBA.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Making the Staging Area">
      <p>To start a product service, we'll create a directory
	structure that will hold software components (jar files) as
	well as scripts that will simplify the usually over-long Java
	command lines.  (Note that these examples are for Mac OS X,
	Linux, or other Unix-like systems.  Windows users will have to
	adapt.)
      </p>

      <p>Let's start by making a directory hierarchy for our product
	service called <code>ps</code> (this example uses a C-style
	shell <code>csh</code>, if you're using <code>bash</code> or
	another style shell, substitute the appropriate commands).
      </p>

      <source>% <b>mkdir ps</b>
% <b>cd ps</b>
% <b>setenv PS_HOME `pwd`</b>
% <b>mkdir bin lib</b>
% <b>ls -RF $PS_HOME</b>
bin/    lib/

/Users/kelly/tmp/ps/bin:

/Users/kelly/tmp/ps/lib:</source>

      <p>Note that we're using an environment variable
	<code>PS_HOME</code> to contain the path of the directory
	we're using to hold everything.  We'll use this environment
	variable as we develop the scripts to launch the product service.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="The RMI Registry">
      <p>Since we're using Remote Method Invocation (RMI) for this
	tutorial, we'll need to start an RMI Registry.  An RMI
	Registry serves as a catalog that maps between named objects,
	such as your product server, to the appropriate network
	address and port where the object can be located.  Your
	product client will use the RMI registry to locate the product
	server so it can connect to the product server and communicate with it.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Collecting the RMI Registry Components">
	<p>To start an RMI Registry, you'll need the following components:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><a href="/edm-commons/">EDM Common Components</a>.
	    These are common utilities used by every OODT
	    service.</li> <li><a href="/grid-product/">Grid Product
	    Service</a>.  This is the product service, product client,
	    query handler interface, and related classes.</li> <li><a
	    href="/rmi-registry/">OODT RMI Registry</a>.  This is the
	    actual RMI registry.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>Download each component's binary distribution, unpack each
	  one, and take collect the jar files into the
	  <code>lib</code> directory.  For example:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>cp /tmp/edm-commons-2.2.5/*.jar $PS_HOME/lib</b>
% <b>cp /tmp/grid-product-3.0.3/*.jar $PS_HOME/lib</b>
% <b>cp /tmp/rmi-registry-1.0.0/*.jar $PS_HOME/lib</b>
% <b>ls -l $PS_HOME/lib</b>
total 312
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  149503 24 Feb 14:06 edm-commons-2.2.5.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  120844 24 Feb 14:07 grid-product-3.0.3.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly    8055 24 Feb 14:07 rmi-registry-1.0.0.jar</source>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Writing the RMI Script">
	<p>To keep from having to type long Java command lines, we'll
	  create a simple shell script that will start the RMI
	  registry.  We'll call it <code>rmi-reg</code> and stick it
	  in the <code>bin</code> directory.
	</p>

	<p>Here's the <code>rmi-reg</code> script:</p>
	<source>#!/bin/sh
exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
    gov.nasa.jpl.oodt.rmi.RMIRegistry</source>

	<p>This script tells the Java virtual machine to find
	  extension jars in the directory <code>$PS_HOME/lib</code>.  It
	  then says that the main class to execute is
	  <code>gov.nasa.jpl.oodt.rmi.RMIRegistry</code>.
	</p>

	<p>Go ahead and make this script executable and start the RMI
	  Registry. In another window (with the appropriate setting of
	  <code>PS_HOME</code>), run
	  <code>$PS_HOME/bin/rmi-reg</code>.  You should see output
	  similar to the following:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>chmod 755 $PS_HOME/bin/rmi-reg</b>
% <b>$PS_HOME/bin/rmi-reg</b>
Thu Feb 24 14:10:25 CST 2005: no objects registered</source>

	<p>The RMI Registry is now running.  Every two minutes it will
	  display an update of all registered objects.  Naturally, we
	  don't have any product service running right now, so it will
	  say <code>no objects registered</code>.  Go ahead and ignore
	  this window for now.  It's time to start our product server.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="The Product Server">
      <p>With an RMI Registry in place, we're ready to start our
	product server.  As with the RMI Registry, we'll need the
	software components and to make a script to launch it.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Collecting the Product Server Components">
	<p>We already have two of the components needed to start the
	  product server, <code>edm-commons</code> and
	  <code>grid-product</code>.  We need two more:
	</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><a href="/edm-query/">EDM Query Expression</a>.  This
	  component encapsulates the implementation of an OODT query
	  and also contains some product retrieval utilities.</li>
	  <li><a href="http://ws.apache.org/xmlrpc">Apache
	  XML-RPC</a>.  This is used internally by OODT services.
	  Download version 1.1, not a later version!  If you prefer,
	  you can <a
	  href="http://ibiblio.org/maven/xmlrpc/jars/xmlrpc-1.1.jar">fetch
	  the jar file directly</a>.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>As before, put these jars into the
	  <code>$PS_HOME/lib</code> directory:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>ls -l $PS_HOME/lib</b>
total 376
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  149503 24 Feb 14:06 edm-commons-2.2.5.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly   43879 24 Feb 14:35 edm-query-2.0.2.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  120844 24 Feb 14:07 grid-product-3.0.3.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly    8055 24 Feb 14:07 rmi-registry-1.0.0.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly   53978 24 Feb 14:35 xmlrpc-1.1.jar</source>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Writing the Product Server Script">
	<p>To launch the product server, we'll create a script called
	  <code>ps</code> in the <code>$PS_HOME/bin</code> directory.
	  Here's its contents:
	</p>

	<source>#!/bin/sh
exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
    jpl.eda.ExecServer \
    jpl.eda.product.rmi.ProductServiceImpl \
    urn:eda:rmi:MyProductService</source>

	<p>Like with the RMI server, this tells Java where to find
	  extension jars (<code>$PS_HOME/lib</code>).  The main class
	  is <code>jpl.eda.ExecServer</code>, this is a framework
	  class from <code>edm-commons</code> that provides basic
	  start-up functions for a variety of services.  In this case,
	  the service is
	  <code>jpl.eda.product.rmi.ProductServiceImpl</code>; this is
	  the name of the class that provides the RMI version of the
	  OODT product service.  We then pass in one final
	  command-line argument,
	  <code>urn:eda:rmi:MyProductService</code>.  This names the product service.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="What's in a Name?">
	<p>The product service registers itself using a name provided
	  on the command-line, in this case,
	  <code>urn:eda:rmi:MyProductService</code>.  Let's take apart
	  the name and see how it works.
	</p>

	<p>If you're familiar with web standards, you can see that the
	  name is a Uniform Resource Name (URN), since it starts with
	  <code>urn:</code>.  The OODT Framework uses URNs to identify
	  services and other objects.  The <code>eda:</code> tells
	  that the name is part of the Enterprise Data Architecture
	  (EDA) namespace.  (EDA was the name of a project related to
	  OODT that was merged with OODT.  For now, just always use
	  <code>eda:</code> in your URNs.)
	</p>
	
	<p>Next comes <code>rmi:</code>.  This is a special flag for
	  the OODT services that tells that we're using a name of an
	  RMI-accessible object.  The OODT framework will know to use
	  an RMI Registry to register the server. 
	</p>

	<p>Finally is <code>MyProductService</code>.  This is the
	  actual name used in the RMI Registry.  You can call your
	  product service anything you want.  For example, suppose you
	  have three product servers; one in the US, one in Canada,
	  and one in Australia.  You might name them:
	</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><code>urn:eda:rmi:US</code></li>
	  <li><code>urn:eda:rmi:Canada</code></li>
	  <li><code>urn:eda:rmi:Australia</code></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Or you might prefer to use ISO country codes.  Or you might
	  name them according to the kinds of products they serve,
	  such as <code>urn:eda:rmi:Biomarkers</code> or
	  <code>urn:eda:rmi:BusniessForecasts</code>.
	</p>

	<p>The RMI Registry will happily re-assign a name if one's
	  already in use, so when deploying your own product servers,
	  be sure to give each one a unique name.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Launching the Product Server">
	<p>Make the <code>ps</code> script executable and start the
	  product server at this time.  Do this in a separate window
	  with the appropriate setting of <code>PS_HOME</code>:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>chmod 755 $PS_HOME/bin/ps</b>
% <b>$PS_HOME/bin/ps</b>
Object context ready; delegating to: [jpl.eda.object.jndi.RMIContext@94257f]</source>

	<p>The product service is now running and ready to accept
	  product queries.  Since we didn't tell it what query
	  handlers to use, it will always respond with zero matching
	  products.  That may not be interesting, but it's a good test
	  to see if we can at least launch a product server.  Now,
	  let's launch a product client and query it.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Querying the Product Server">
      <p>To query the product server, we use a product client.  The
	Java class <code>jpl.eda.product.ProductClient</code> provides
	the API for your own programs to query for and retrieve
	products.  But it's also an executable class, so we can run it
	from the command-line in order to test our product server.
	However, let's again make a script to make invoking it a bit
	easier.
      </p>

      <p>We'll call the script <code>pc</code> for "product client,"
	and it will take a single command line argument, which will be
	the <em>query expression</em> to pass into the product server.
	Query expressions define the constraints on the kinds of
	products we want to achieve.  Since the product server we've
	set up will always respond with zero products, though, we can
	pass in any syntactically valid query expression.
      </p>

      <p>Here's the script:</p>

      <source>#!/bin/sh
if [ $# -ne 1 ]; then
   echo "Usage: `basename $0` &lt;query-expression&gt;" 1>&amp;2
   exit 1
fi

exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
     jpl.eda.product.ProductClient \
     -out \
     urn:eda:rmi:MyProductService \
     "$1"</source>


      <p>This script checks to make sure there's exactly one
	command-line argument, the query expression.  If there isn't,
	it prints a helpful usage message to the standard error
	stream, as is Unix tradition.  Otherwise, it will execute the
	<code>jpl.eda.product.ProductClient</code> class with Java.
	When executed, this class expects three command-line arguments:
      </p>

      <ol>
	<li><code>-out</code> or <code>-xml</code>.  OODT uses XML to
	  represent the query that it passes to and receives back from
	  a product server.  With <code>-out</code>, the product
	  client will write to the standard output the raw product
	  data.  With <code>-xml</code>, you'll instead see the XML
	  representation of the query (with any embedded matching
	  products) instead.
	</li>

	<li>The name of the product service to contact.  In this case,
	  we're using the one we started earlier, registered under the
	  name <code>urn:eda:rmi:MyProductService</code>.
	</li>

	<li>The query expression.</li>
      </ol>

      <p>Now we can make this script executable and run it:</p>

      <source>% <b>chmod 755 $PS_HOME/bin/pc</b>
<b>$PS_HOME/bin/pc "x = 3"</b>
Object context ready; delegating to: [jpl.eda.object.jndi.RMIContext@c79809]
No matching results</source>

      <p>Although not terribly exciting, this is good news.  Here's
	what happened:
      </p>

      <ol>
	<li>The product client created a query object (of class
	  <code>jpl.eda.xmlquery.XMLQuery</code> from the
	  <code>edm-query</code> component) out of the string query
	  <code>x = 3</code>.
	</li>

	<li>It asked the RMI Registry to tell it where (network
	  address) it could find the product service named
	  <code>MyProductService</code>.
	</li>

	<li>After getting the response back from the RMI Registry, it
	  then contacted the product service over a network connection
	  (even if to the same local system) and asked it to handle
	  the query, passing the query object.
	</li>

	<li>The product service, having no query handlers to which to
	  delegate, merely returned the query object unmodified over
	  the network connection.
	</li>

	<li>The product client, having no product to write to the
	  standard output (as indicated by the <code>-out</code>
	  argument), wrote the diagnostic message <code>No matching
	  results</code>.
	</li>
      </ol>

      <p>You can make this example slightly more interesting by
	changing the <code>-out</code> in the <code>pc</code> script
	to <code>-xml</code>.  Now, when you run it, you'll see an XML
	document describing the query.  One of the pertinent sections
	to note is:
      </p>

      <source>...&lt;queryResultSet/&gt;...</source>

      <p>This empty XML element means that there were no results.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Conclusion">
      <p>By following this tutorial, you've started both an RMI
	Registry and a basic product server.  You've queried that
	product server to insure that you can communicate with it.  In
	later tutorials, you'll build on this product server by adding
	a query handler to it and returning actual product data.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
