<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Developing a Query Handler</title>
    <author email="Sean.Kelly@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Kelly</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Developing a Query Handler">
      <p>In the <a href="../ps/">last tutorial</a>, we started a
	product server.  But this wasn't a very useful product server;
	it could answer queries but always respond with no results.
	That's because it had no query handlers.  Query handlers have
	the responsibility of actually handling product queries.  In
	this tutorial, we'll develop a query handler, install it into
	our product server, and query it to see if it works.
      </p>

      <p>To do this tutorial, you'll need mastery of two things:</p>
      <ul>
	<li>Using the <code>XMLQuery</code> class.  Follow the <a
	    href="/edm-query/tutorial/">query expression tutorail</a>
	    now if you're not familiar with it.
	</li>

	<li>Running and querying a product server.  Follow the <a
	    href="../ps/">Your First Product Server</a> tutorial to
	    get your product server up and running.  In this tutorial,
	    we'll build on that product server, so it's especially
	    important to have it in good shape.
	</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="Serving Up Constants">
      <p>Product servers delegate to query handlers.  It's the job of
	query handlers to interpret incoming queries (expressed as
	<code>XMLQuery</code> objects), search for, retrieve, convert,
	or synthesize matching product results, adorn the
	<code>XMLQuery</code> object with <code>Result</code> objects,
	and return the modified query.  At that point the OODT
	framework takes over again and tries other installed query
	handlers, eventually returning the completed
	<code>XMLQuery</code> back to the product client that made the
	query in the first place.
      </p>

      <p>We'll make a query handler that serves mathematical
	constants.  Have you ever been in a position where you needed,
	say, the value of the third Flajolet number or perhaps
	Zeta(9)?  No?  Well, just pretend for now you did.  What we'll
	do is develop a query handler for a product server that will
	serve values of various mathematical constants.
      </p>

      <p>The approach we'll take has three simple steps:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>Get some handy constants.</li>
	<li>Define the query expression.</li>
	<li>Write a query handler.  The query handler will:
	  <ol>
	    <li>Examine the query expression to see if it's a request
	      for a constant, and if so, what constant is
	      requested.
	    </li>
	    <li>Examine the query's list of acceptable MIME types.</li>
	    <li>If both check out, look up the desired constant's value.</li>
	    <li>If found, add it as a <code>Result</code> in the <code>XMLQuery</code>.</li>
	  </ol>
	</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section name="Writing the Code">
      <p>In this section, we'll build up the query handler source code
	in pieces, examining each piece thoroughly.  We'll then
	present the entire source file.
      </p>

      <subsection name='Gathering Handy Constants'>
	<p>The wonderful world of science and mathematics is replete
	  with useful constant values.  For this example, let's just pick three:
	</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><var>pi</var> = 3.14159265...</li>
	  <li><var>e</var> = 2.7182818285...</li>
	  <li><var>gamma</var> = 0.577215664...</li>
	</ul>

	<p>In Java code, we can set up those values as a
	  <code>Map</code> in a static field.  Thus we start forming our
	  source file, <code>ConstantHandler.java</code>:
	</p>

	<source>import java.util.HashMap;
import java.util.Map;
import jpl.eda.product.QueryHandler;
public class ConstantHandler
  implements QueryHandler {
  private static final Map CONSTANTS = new HashMap();
  static {
    CONSTANTS.put("pi",    "3.14159265...");
    CONSTANTS.put("e",     "2.7182818285...");
    CONSTANTS.put("gamma", "0.577215664...");
  }
}</source>

	<p>As you can see, we're storing both the constant name and its
	  value as <code>java.lang.String</code> objects.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name='Defining the Query Expression'>
	<p>Recall that the <code>XMLQuery</code> class can use parsed
	  queries (where it generates postfix boolean stacks) or
	  unparsed ones.  While unparsed ones are easier, we'll go with
	  parsed ones to demonstrate how on the server-side you deal
	  with those postfix stacks.
	</p>

	<p>Using the XMLQuery's expression language, we'll look for
	  queries of the form:</p>
	
	<p><code>constant = <var>name</var></code></p>

	<p>where <var>name</var> is the name of a constant.  That will
	  form a postfix "where" stack with exactly three
	  <code>QueryElement</code> objects on it:
	</p>

	<ol>
	  <li>The first (top) <code>QueryElement</code> will have role =
	    <code>elemName</code> and value = <code>constant</code>.
	  </li>

	  <li>The second (middle) <code>QueryElement</code> will have
	    role = <code>LITERAL</code> and a value equal to the
	    constant <var>name</var>.
	  </li>

	  <li>The third (bottom) <code>QueryElement</code> will have
	    role = <code>RELOP</code> and value = <code>EQ</code>.
	  </li>
	</ol>

	<p>If we get any other kind of stack, we'll reject it and return
	  no matching results.  That's reasonable behavior; after all, a
	  query for <code>donutsEaten &gt; 5 AND RETURN =
	    episodeNumber</code> may be handled by a
	  <code>SimpsonsEpisodeQueryHandler</code> that's <em>also</em>
	  installed in the same product server.
	</p>

	<p>We'll define a utility method, <code>getConstantName</code>,
	  that will take the <code>XMLQuery</code>, check for the
	  postfix "where" stack as described, and return the matching
	  constant <var>name</var>.  If it gets a stack whose structure
	  doesn't match, it will return <code>null</code>.  We'll add
	  this method to our <code>ConstantHandler.java</code> file:
	</p>

	<source>import java.util.List;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.XMLQuery;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.QueryElement;
...
public class ConstantHandler
  implements QueryHandler {
  ...
  private static String getConstantName(XMLQuery q) {
    List stack = q.getWhereElementSet();
    if (stack.size() != 3) return null;
    QueryElement e = (QueryElement) stack.get(0);
    if (!"elemName".equals(e.getRole())
      || !"constant".equals(e.getValue()))
      return null;
    e = (QueryElement) stack.get(2);
    if (!"RELOP".equals(e.getRole())
      || !"EQ".equals(e.getValue()))
      return null;
    e = (QueryElement) stack.get(1);
    if (!"LITERAL".equals(e.getRole()))
	return null;
    return e.getValue();
  }
}</source>

	<p>Here, we first check to make sure there's exactly three
	  elements, returning null if not.  There's no need to go further.
	</p>

	<p>Assuming there's three elements, the code then checks the
	  topmost element.  For an expression <code>constant =
	    <var>name</var></code>, the topmost element will have role
	  <code>elemName</code> and value <code>constant</code>.  If
	  neither condition is true, we return null right away.  No need
	  to check further.
	</p>

	<p>If the topmost element checks out, we then check the
	  bottommost element.  For <code>constant =
	    <var>name</var></code>, the bottom element is generated from
	  the equals sign.  It will have role <code>RELOP</code>
	  (relational operator) and value <code>EQ</code>, meaning
	  "equals".
	</p>

	<p>If it checks out, all we have to do is check the middle
	  element.  The infix expression <code>constant =
	    <var>name</var></code> generates a postfix middle element of
	  <var>name</var> as the value, with a role of
	  <code>LITERAL</code>.  We make sure it's <code>LITERAL</code>.
	  If not, we're done; it's not a valid expression for our query
	  handler.
	</p>

	<p>But if so, then the value of that query element is the name
	  of the desired constant.  So we return it, regardless of what
	  it is.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name='Checking for Acceptable MIME Types'>
	<p>Since all of our mathematical constants are strings, we'll
	  say that the result MIME type of our products is
	  <code>text/plain</code>.  That means that any incoming
	  <code>XMLQuery</code> must include any of the following MIME types:
	</p>
	<ol>
	  <li><code>text/plain</code></li>
	  <li><code>text/*</code></li>
	  <li><code>*/*</code></li>
	</ol>
	<p>All of these match <code>text/plain</code>, which is the only
	  product type we're capable of serving.  (In your own product
	  servers, you might have more complex logic; for example, you
	  could write code to draw the numbers into an image file if the
	  requested type is <code>image/jpeg</code> ... but I wouldn't
	  want to.)
	</p>
	<p>To support this in our query handler, we'll write another
	  utility method.  It'll be called
	  <code>isAcceptableType</code>, and it will take the
	  <code>XMLQuery</code> and examine it to see what MIME types
	  are acceptable to the caller.  If it finds any of the ones in
	  the above list, it will return <code>true</code>, and the
	  caller can continue to process the query.  If not, it will
	  return <code>false</code>, and the query handler will stop
	  processing and return the <code>XMLQuery</code> unadorned with
	  any results.
	</p>
	<p>Here's the code:</p>

	<source>import java.util.Iterator;
...
public class ConstantHandler
  implements QueryHandler {
  ...
  private static boolean isAcceptableType(XMLQuery q) {
    List mimes = q.getMimeAccept();
    if (mimes.isEmpty()) return true;
    for (Iterator i = mimes.iterator(); i.hasNext();) {
      String type = (String) i.next();
      if ("text/plain".equals(type)
        || "text/*".equals(type)
        || "*/*".equals(type)) return true;
    }
    return false;
  }
}</source>

	<p>Here, we check if the list of acceptable MIME types is empty.
	  An empty list is the same as saying <code>*/*</code>, so that
	  automatically says we've got an acceptable type.  For a
	  non-empty list, we go through each type one-by-one.  If it's
	  any of the strings <code>text/plain</code>,
	  <code>text/*</code>, or <code>*/*</code>, then that's an
	  acceptable type.
	</p>

	<p>However, if we get through the entire list and we don't find
	  any type that the user wants that we can provide, we return
	  <code>false</code>.  The query handler will check for a
	  <code>false</code> value and return early from handling the
	  query, leaving the <code>XMLQuery</code> untouched.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name='Inserting the Result'>
	<p>Assuming the query handler has found an acceptable MIME type,
	  and has found a valid query and the name of the desired
	  constant, it can lookup the constant in the
	  <code>CONSTANTS</code> map.  And assuming it finds a matching
	  constant in that map, it can insert the value as a
	  <code>Result</code> object.
	</p>

	<p>To insert the constant's value, we'll develop yet another
	  utility method, this time called <code>insert</code>.  This
	  method will take the name of the constant, its value, and the
	  <code>XMLQuery</code>.  It will add a <code>Result</code>
	  object to the <code>XMLQuery</code>.  When the query handler
	  returns this modified <code>XMLQuery</code> object, the
	  framework will return it to the product client, which can then
	  display the matching result.
	</p>

	<p><code>Result</code> objects can also have optional
	  <code>Header</code> objects that serve as "column headings"
	  for tabular like results.  Our result isn't tabular, it's just
	  a single value, but we'll add a heading anyway just to
	  demonstrate how it's done.  (You could argue that it's a
	  one-by-one table, too!)  The header's name will be the same as
	  the constant's name; the data type will be <code>real</code>
	  and the units will be <code>none</code>.
	</p>

	<p>Here's the code:</p>

	<source>import java.util.Collections;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.Header;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.Result;
...
public class ConstantHandler
  implements QueryHandler {
  ...
  private static void insert(String name,
    String value, XMLQuery q) {
    Header h = new Header(name, "real", "none");
    Result r = new Result(name, "text/plain",
      /*profileID*/null, /*resourceID*/null,
      Collections.singletonList(h),
      value, /*classified*/false, Result.INFINITE);
    q.getResults().add(r);
  }
}</source>

	<p>In this method, we first create the header.  Then we create
	  the result; the result's ID (which differentiates it from
	  other results in the same <code>XMLQuery</code> is just the
	  name of the constant.  Its MIME type is
	  <code>text/plain</code>.  We set the profile ID and resource
	  ID fields to <code>null</code>, as recommended back in the <a
	    href="/edm-query/tutorial/">XMLQuery Tutorial</a>.  Then we
	  add our sole header.  Then we add the mathematical constant's
	  value.  Finally, this constant isn't classified, so we set the
	  classified flag to <code>false</code>.  Also, these
	  mathematical constants should be valid forever, so we set the
	  validity period to <code>Result.INFINITE</code>, a special
	  value that means a never-ending validity period.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name='Handling the Query'>
	<p>With all of these utility methods in hand, it's easy to
	  handle the query now.  The
	  <code>jpl.eda.product.QueryHandler</code> interface
	  specifies a single method that we must implement,
	  <code>query</code>.  This method accepts an
	  <code>XMLQuery</code> object and returns an
	  <code>XMLQuery</code> object.  The returned one may or may
	  not be adorned with matching results.
	</p>

	<p>Here's what we have to do:</p>
	<ol>
	  <li>Get the constant name with <code>getConstantName</code>.
	    If we get <code>null</code>, it means the query's not of
	    the form <code>constant = <var>name</var></code>, so we
	    ignore it.
	  </li>

	  <li>See if the user's willing to accept a
	    <code>text/plain</code> MIME type.  If not, we ignore this query.
	  </li>

	  <li>Find the constant in our <code>CONSTANTS</code> map.  If
	    it's not there, we ignore this query.
	  </li>

	  <li>Insert the constant's value into the <code>XMLQuery</code>.</li>

	  <li>Returned the modified <code>XMLQuery</code>.</li>
	</ol>

	<p>The source:</p>

	<source>public class ConstantHandler
  implements QueryHandler {
  ...
  public XMLQuery query(XMLQuery q) {
    String name = getConstantName(q);
    if (name == null) return q;
    if (!isAcceptableType(q)) return q;
    String value = (String) CONSTANTS.get(name);
    if (value == null) return q;
    insert(name, value, q);
    return q;
  }
}</source>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name='Complete Source Code'>
	<p>Here is the complete source file,
	<code>ConstantHandler.java</code>:</p>

	<source>import java.util.Collections;
import java.util.HashMap;
import java.util.Iterator;
import java.util.List;
import java.util.Map;
import jpl.eda.product.QueryHandler;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.Header;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.Result;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.QueryElement;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.XMLQuery;

public class ConstantHandler
  implements QueryHandler {
  private static final Map CONSTANTS = new HashMap();
  static {
    CONSTANTS.put("pi",    "3.14159265...");
    CONSTANTS.put("e",     "2.7182818285...");
    CONSTANTS.put("gamma", "0.577215664...");
  }
  private static String getConstantName(XMLQuery q) {
    List stack = q.getWhereElementSet();
    if (stack.size() != 3) return null;
    QueryElement e = (QueryElement) stack.get(0);
    if (!"elemName".equals(e.getRole())
      || !"constant".equals(e.getValue()))
      return null;
    e = (QueryElement) stack.get(2);
    if (!"RELOP".equals(e.getRole())
      || !"EQ".equals(e.getValue()))
      return null;
    e = (QueryElement) stack.get(1);
    if (!"LITERAL".equals(e.getRole()))
	return null;
    return e.getValue();
  }
  private static boolean isAcceptableType(XMLQuery q) {
    List mimes = q.getMimeAccept();
    if (mimes.isEmpty()) return true;
    for (Iterator i = mimes.iterator(); i.hasNext();) {
      String type = (String) i.next();
      if ("text/plain".equals(type)
        || "text/*".equals(type)
        || "*/*".equals(type)) return true;
    }
    return false;
  }
  private static void insert(String name,
    String value, XMLQuery q) {
    Header h = new Header(name, "real", "none");
    Result r = new Result(name, "text/plain",
      /*profileID*/null, /*resourceID*/null,
      Collections.singletonList(h),
      value, /*classified*/false, Result.INFINITE);
    q.getResults().add(r);
  }
  public XMLQuery query(XMLQuery q) {
    String name = getConstantName(q);
    if (name == null) return q;
    if (!isAcceptableType(q)) return q;
    String value = (String) CONSTANTS.get(name);
    if (value == null) return q;
    insert(name, value, q);
    return q;
  }
}</source>

	<p>How should you go about compiling this and installing it in
	  a product server?  Read on!
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Compiling the Code">
      <p>We'll compile this code using the J2SDK command-line tools,
	but if you're more comfortable with some kind of Integrated
	Development Environment (IDE), adjust as necessary.
      </p>

      <p>First, let's go back to the <code>$PS_HOME</code> directory
	we made earlier and make directories to hold both the source
	code and classes that we'll compile from it:
      </p>

      <source>% <b>cd $PS_HOME</b>
% <b>mkdir classes src</b></source>

      <p>Then, create <code>$PS_HOME/src/ConstantHandler.java</code> using
	your favorite text editor (or by cutting and pasting the source
	from this page, or whatever).  Finally, compile the file as follows:
      </p>

      <source>% <b>javac -extdirs lib \
  -d classes src/ConstantHandler.java</b>
% ls -l classes
total 4
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  2524 25 Feb 15:46 ConstantHandler.class</source>

      <p>The <code>javac</code> command is the Java compiler.  The
	<code>-extdirs lib</code> arguments tell the compiler where to
	find extension jars.  In this case, the code references things
	defined in edm-query-2.0.2.jar and grid-product-3.0.3.jar.
	The <code>-d classes</code> tells where compiled classes
	should go.
      </p>

      <p>Next, make a jar file that contains your compiled class:</p>

      <source>% <b>jar -cf lib/my-handlers.jar \
  -C classes ConstantHandler.class</b>
% <b>jar -tf lib/my-handlers.jar</b>
META-INF/
META-INF/MANIFEST.MF
ConstantHandler.class</source>

      <p>We now have a new jar file of our own creation in the
	<code>$PS_HOME/lib</code> directory; this means that the
	product server will be able to find out new query handler.
	All we have to do now is tell our product server about it.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name='Specfying the Query Handler'>
      <p>Query handlers aren't really <em>installed</em> into product
	servers.  What you do is tell the product server what query
	handlers you want it to use by naming their classes.  The
	product server will instantiate an object of each class and,
	as queries come in, it will delegate queries to each
	instantiated query handler.
      </p>

      <p>To tell a product server what query handlers to instantiate,
	you specify a system property called <code>handlers</code>.
	You set this property to a comma-separated list of class
	names.  These should be fully-qualified class names (with
	package prefixes, if you used packages when making your query
	handlers), separated by commas.  In this tutorial, we made
	just one query handler, and we didn't put it into a package,
	so we'll just use <code>ConstantHandler</code>.
      </p>

      <p>First, stop any product server you have running now by
	pressing CTRL+C (or whatever your interrupt key is) in the
	window that was running the product server.  Next, modify the
	<code>$PS_HOME/bin/ps</code> file so it reads as follows:
      </p>

      <source>#!/bin/sh
exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
    -Dhandlers=ConstantHandler \
    jpl.eda.ExecServer \
    jpl.eda.product.rmi.ProductServiceImpl \
    urn:eda:rmi:MyProductService</source>

      <p>We specified a system property on the command line using
	Java's <code>-D</code> option.  This defines the system
	property <code>handlers</code> as having the value
	<code>ConstantHandler</code>.  Finally, start the product
	server again by running <code>$PS_HOME/bin/ps</code>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name='Querying for Constants'>
      <p>Once again, edit the <code>$PS_HOME/bin/pc</code> script and
	change <code>-xml</code> back to <code>-out</code> so that
	instead of the XML output we'll see the raw product data.
	Then run it and see what happens:
      </p>

      <source>% <b>$PS_HOME/bin/pc 'constant = pi'</b>
3.14159265...% </source>

      <p>Because the raw product data was the string
	<code>3.14159265...</code> without any trailing newline, the
	shell's prompt appeared right at the end of the product
	result.  You might try piping the output of the above command
	through a pager like <code>more</code> or <code>less</code> to
	avoid this.
      </p>

      <p>Here's what happened when we ran this command:</p>

      <ol>
	<li>The product client created an <code>XMLQuery</code> object
	  out of the string query <code>constant = pi</code>.
	</li>

	<li>It asked the RMI Registry to tell it where (network
	  address) it could find the product service named
	  <code>MyProductService</code>.
	</li>

	<li>After getting the response back from the RMI Registry, it
	  then contacted the product service over a network connection
	  (even if to the same local system) and asked it to handle
	  the query, passing the query object.
	</li>

	<li>The product service had only one query handler, the
	  <code>ConstantHandler</code>, to which to delegate, so it
	  passed the XMLQuery to it.
	</li>

	<li>The <code>ConstantHandler</code>'s <code>query</code>
	  method was called.  It checked if the query was the kind it
	  wanted, extracted the desired mathematical constant's name,
	  checked for an acceptable requested MIME type, looked up the
	  constant's value, inserted it as a <code>Result</code> into
	  the <code>XMLQuery</code>, and returned the modified query.
	</li>

	<li>The product service, seeing it had no other handlers to
	  try, returned the modified <code>XMLQuery</code> to the
	  product client over the network connection.
	</li>

	<li>The product client took the first <code>Result</code> out
	  of the <code>XMLQuery</code>, called
	  <code>Result.getInputStream</code>, and copied each byte of
	  the result to the standard output.  This wrote
	  <code>3.14159265...</code> to your window.
	</li>
      </ol>

      <p>If you change the <code>$PS_HOME/bin/pc</code> script again
	so that instead of <code>-out</code> it's <code>-xml</code>,
	you'll again see the XMLQuery as an XML document.  The interesting part is the <code>&lt;queryResultSet&gt;</code>:
      </p>

      <source><![CDATA[<queryResultSet>
  <resultElement classified="false" validity="-1">
    <resultId>pi</resultId>
    <resultMimeType>text/plain</resultMimeType>
    <profId/>
    <identifier/>
    <resultHeader>
      <headerElement>
	<elemName>pi</elemName>
	<elemType>real</elemType>
	<elemUnit>none</elemUnit>
      </headerElement>
    </resultHeader>
    <resultValue xml:space="preserve">3.14159265...</resultValue>
  </resultElement>
</queryResultSet>]]></source>

      <p>I'll let you figure out how this maps to the
	<code>Result</code> object we created in the code.  OK, so is
	this really interesting?  Not really, except to note that the
	actual result data, <code>3.1415265...</code>, appears in the
	XML document.  In the OODT framework, we call this a "small"
	result, because the product data was embedded in the XMLQuery
	object.  Text data like <code>text/plain</code> products
	appear just as text.  Binary data like <code>image/jpeg</code>
	and <code>application/octet-stream</code> get base-64 encoded
	into text.
      </p>
      <p>As you can guess, there's a point at which encoded data goes
	from being nice and small and tidy to just too large to
	contain in a single object.  In the OODT framework, we can use
	a special query handler for such large products, but that's
	another tutorial.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name='Conclusion'>
      <p>In this tutorial, we learned how to write a complete query
	handler for a product server, including handling of postfix
	boolean "where" stacks, lists of acceptable MIME types, and
	result headers.  We compiled the query handler, put it into a
	jar file, and specified it to our product server.  And we
	could even query it and get data back.
      </p>

      <p>Don't toss out this product server yet, though.  Another
	tutorial will use it and cover the infamous
	<code>LargeProductQueryHandler</code>.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
