<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
license agreements.  See the NOTICE.txt file distributed with this work for
additional information regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this
file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not
use this file except in compliance with the License.  You may obtain a copy of
the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  See the
License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under
the License.
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Using Maven</title>
    <author email="woollard@jpl.nasa.gov">David Woollard</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Using Maven">
      <p>OODT uses <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> for 
      managing our build environment. Maven is an open source product from the 
      <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a> that improves 
      on <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">Ant</a> in the area of build management, 
      which it turn was an improvement on Make. This document describes the use of 
      Maven for OODT build management.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Setup">
      <p>Maven can be downloaded from the 
      <a href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">Maven Download</a> 
      page. OODT is using version 2.0 and above. Maven was developed in Java so it 
      will run on the popular platforms (e.g., Windows, Mac OSX, etc.). Beyond 
      making sure the <i>mvn</i> executable is in your path, there is very little 
      setup required.</p>

      <p>Maven is based on the concept of a Project Object Model (POM) which is 
      contained in the <i>pom.xml</i> file found at the root of each project. 
      The POM allows Maven to manage a project's build, reporting and documentation. 
      For OODT, much of the default information for managing the projects is 
      contained in a parent POM, which is located in the <i>oodt-core</i> project. So, 
      in order to build any of the other projects (e.g., cas-curator, cas-filemgr, 
      etc.) the parent POM must be downloaded from the OODT Maven repository. The 
      local <i>pom.xml</i> files for each of the projects have been configured to 
      retrieve the parent POM automatically.</p>
      
      <p>Once Maven has been setup, the first step to building a project with Maven 
      is to checkout a project's source code into the developer's work area. See the 
      <a href="../development/subversion.html">Using Subversion</a> document for how to 
      check out projects from the CM repository.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Project Structure">
      <p>In order for default Maven functions to operate properly, there is a 
      suggested project directory structure. The structure is as follows:</p>
      
      <source>
/
  src/             Source Code (everything)
    main/            Program Source
      assembly/        Package Descriptor
      java/            Java Source
      resources/       Scripts, Config File, etc.
        ...
    test/            Test Source
      java/
      resources/
        ...
    site/            Site Documentation
      apt/             Docs in APT Format
        index.apt
        ...
      xdoc/            Docs in XDOC Format
        index.xml
        ...
      resources/
        images/
      site.xml         Menu Structure

  target/          Build Results (binaries, docs and packages)
    ...

  LICENSE.txt
  README.txt
  pom.xml          Project Object Model (POM)
      </source>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Standard Commands">
    <p>There are few standard commands that developers will use on a daily basis 
    and they are related to building and cleaning a project.</p>
    <subsection name="Build a Project">
      <p>Build the project's libraries and executables with the following 
      command:</p>
      <source>
mvn compile
      </source>
      <p>The above command will generate the artifacts in the <i>target/</i> 
      directory.</p>      
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Install a Project">
      <p>Install the project's artifacts locally with the following command:</p>
      <source>
mvn install
      </source>
      <p>Prior to installation, the above command will compile the source code, 
      if necessary, and execute the unit tests. The result of the above command 
      is to install the generated artifacts (e.g. pom, jar, etc.) in the user's 
      local Maven repository ($HOME/.m2/repository/). This is useful when the 
      artifact is a dependency for another project but has yet to be deployed 
      to the SWSA Maven repository.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Package a Project">
      <p>Create the project's distribution package with the following command:</p>
      <source>
mvn package
      </source>
      <p>Prior to package creation, the above command will compile the source 
      code, if necessary, and execute the unit tests. The above command will 
      create the package(s) in the target/ directory.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Build a Project's Web Site">
      <p>Build the project's web site with the following command:</p>
      <source>
mvn site
      </source>
      <p>The above command will generate the web site in the <i>target/site/</i>
      directory. View the site by pointing your web browser at the 
      <i>index.html</i> file within that directory.</p>
    </subsection> 
    <subsection name="Clean a Project">
      <p>Clean out the project directory of generated artifacts with the 
      following command:</p>
      <source>
mvn clean
      </source>
      <p>The above command will remove the <i>target/</i> directory and its 
      contents.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="Useful Command Arguments">
      <p>There a couple of useful arguments which can be appended to the 
      commands above to limit the scope of the command.</p>
      <p>In order to skip unit test execution, add the following argument:</p>
      <source>
mvn [command] -Dmaven.test.skip=true
      </source>
      <p>The above command is most useful with the <i>install</i>, 
      <i>package</i> and <i>site</i> commands.</p>
      <p>When a project has modules defined in the POM, the command can be 
      performed against the top level of the project instead of the modules by 
      adding the following argument:</p>
      <source>
mvn [command] --non-recursive
      </source>
    </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Acknowledgments">
      <p>Much of the material in this Maven guide was originally authored 
      by Sean Hardman under the sponsorship of NASA Jet Propulsion 
      Laboratory's Planetary Data System. </p>
    </section>
    <section name="References">
      <p>Here is a list of Maven resources:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="http://maven.apache.org/guides/index.html">Online 
        Documentation Index</a></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
