<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Developing a Profile Handler</title>
    <author email="Sean.Kelly@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Kelly</author>
  </properties>
  <!-- Shift - Nexus Overload -->
  <body>
    <section name="Developing a Profile Handler">
      <p>Profiles describe resources. But where do profiles come from?
	From profile handlers. Profile handlers are interchangeable
	components of a profile server that accept queries for
	profiles and return matching profiles. Profile handlers take a
	static or a dynamic collection of information and serve an
	equivalent set of profiles. Developing a new profile handler
	is as simple as writing a Java class that implements a
	specific interface or two.
      </p>

      <p>If you're not already familiar with the <code>XMLQuery</code>
	class, go ahead and <a href="/edm-query/tutorial/">take its
	  tutorial now</a>.  We'll wait!
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>Profile handlers handle queries for profiles.  They're the
	interchangeable part of a profile server that you can develop
	for special needs.  Profile servers delegate all incoming
	requests to zero or more profile handlers, as shown in the
	following class diagram:
      </p>

      <img src="../images/delegation.png" alt="Delegation model" />

      <p>Developing, testing, and deploying a new profile handler
	involves:
      </p>
      <ol>
	<li>Creating a class that implements (however indirectly)
	  the <code>jpl.eda.profile.handlers.ProfileHandler</code> interface.
	</li>
	<li>Creating a new process that runs either the RMI or
	    CORBA <code>ProfileServiceImpl</code> class,
	    specifying the name of your handler class.
	</li>
	<li>Starting the server and sending in queries.
	</li>
      </ol>
      <p>This document describes each of these steps in detail.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Writing the Handler Class">
      <p>Writing the class that handles profile queries and delivers
	profile results is easily the hardest part in developing a new
	kind of profile server.  Profile servers' handlers can serve
	profiles describing static resources, can synthesize profile
	on the fly to describe resources, and can create profile
	metadata for resources that change all the time.
      </p>
      
      <p>Understanding the resources you're trying to describe with
	profiles is the most important thing you can do before
	beginning to write your profile handler:
      </p>

      <ul>
	<li>Do you always have the same set of static resources?
	  If so, you can write a static profile document to describe
	  them and use the
	  <code>LightweightProfileHandler</code>, thus
	  avoiding having to write a new handler at all.
	</li>
	<li>Do you have resources that never change, but may add to or
	  remove from that set?  If so, you can use the
	  <code>OracleProfileImpl</code> handler which uses an Oracle
	  database to store a set of profiles that you can update.
	</li>
	<li>Do you have resources that do change, or that come
	  from a dynamic set of data?  If so, you'll have to write a
	  handler.
	</li>
      </ul>

      <subsection name="Choosing the Handler Interface to Implement">
	<p>The OODT Framework provides two handler interfaces (one is
	  an extension of the other):
	</p>
	<ul>
	  <li><code>jpl.eda.profile.handlers.ProfileHandler</code>
	      is the basic profile handler.  It defines methods for
	    <em>handling</em> searches for profiles.
	  </li>

	  <li><code>jpl.eda.profile.handlers.ProfileManager</code> is an
	    extension that not just <em>handles</em> profile queries
	    but also <em>manages</em> the set of profiles maintained
	    by the server, by providing methods for adding to,
	    removing from, and updating the set of managed profiles.
	  </li>
	</ul>
      
	<p>For nearly all applications, the <code>ProfileHandler</code>
	  interface is sufficient.  If you need to provide profile
	  management capabilities, it still may be handy to start with
	  the <code>ProfileHandler</code> interface, implement and test
	  its methods, and <em>then</em> change to the
	  <code>ProfileManager</code>.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="The ProfileHandler Interface">
	<p>The <code>ProfileHandler</code> interface is
	  as follows:
	</p>

	<source>package jpl.eda.profile.handlers;

import java.util.List;
import jpl.eda.profile.Profile;
import jpl.eda.profile.ProfileException;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.XMLQuery;

public interface ProfileHandler {
  List findProfiles(XMLQuery query) throws ProfileException;
  Profile get(String profID) throws ProfileException;
}</source>

	<p>The two methods are described in detail below.</p>

	<dl>
	  <dt><code>findProfiles</code></dt>
	  <dd>This method accepts a query in the form of an
	    <code>XMLQuery</code> object and returns a
	    Java <code>List</code> of
	    <code>Profile</code> objects that match.  If
	    there are no matches, this method must return an empty
	    list.  If an error occurs, it should throw the
	      <code>ProfileException</code>.

	    <p>This is by far the most used and most important
	      method, and really is the <i>raison
	      d'etre</i> for profile servers.  It's
	      what the OODT Framework uses to allow clients to ask
	      your server for resources based on metadata .
	    </p>
	  </dd>
	  <dt><code>get</code></dt>
	  <dd>This method accepts the ID of a profile in the form
	    of a Java <code>String</code> and returns
	    either a <code>Profile</code> object with that
	    ID or null if the ID is unknown.  This method enables a
	    client to retrieve a profile using a priori knowledge of
	    the profile's ID (perhaps from a previous search).
	  </dd>
	</dl>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="The ProfileManager Interface">
	<p>The <code>ProfileManager</code> interface
	  builds on the <code>ProfileHandler</code>, and is
	  listed below:
	</p>
	<source>package jpl.eda.profile.handlers;

import java.util.Collection;
import java.util.Iterator;
import jpl.eda.profile.Profile;
import jpl.eda.profile.ProfileException;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.XMLQuery;

public interface ProfileManager extends ProfileHandler {
  void add(Profile profile) throws ProfileException;
  void addAll(Collection collection) throws ProfileException;
  void clear() throws ProfileException;
  boolean contains(Profile profile) throws ProfileException;
  boolean containsAll(Collection collection) throws ProfileException;
  Collection getAll() throws ProfileException;
  boolean isEmpty() throws ProfileException;
  Iterator iterator() throws ProfileException;
  boolean remove(String profID, String version) throws ProfileException;
  boolean remove(String profID) throws ProfileException;
  int size() throws ProfileException;
  void replace(Profile profile) throws ProfileException;
}</source>

	<p>If you choose to implement a profile manager, please see
	  the API documentation for the
	  <code>ProfileManager</code> class for the
	  expectations of each method.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Our First Profile Handler">
      <p>Although not terribly useful, a &#8220;null&#8221; profile
	handler is a good example to start with because it is small and
	will make sure your environment is in good working order before
	proceeding to a real profile handler.
      </p>
      
      <p>What's a &#8220;null&#8221; profile handler?  It's one that
	serves no profiles.  That is, for any query with
	<code>findProfiles</code> and any retrieval with
	<code>get</code> it never returns any profiles.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Directory Layout">
	<p>For these examples, we'll work on a kind of Unix system
	  with a <code>csh</code> shell.  Other shell users or Windows
	  users will need to adjust.  We'll also use the J2SDK
	  command-line tools.  If you're using an Integrated
	  Development Environment of some sort, please adjust
	  accordingly.
	</p>

	<p>We'll create a "home" directory for our profile servers
	  with subdirectories to hold specific components like source
	  code, jar files, and scripts.  We'll call this home
	  directory by an environment variable, <code>PS_HOME</code>
	  (PS for Profile Server), so that scripts won't have to refer
	  to things by relative paths:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>mkdir ps</b>
% <b>cd ps</b>
% <b>setenv PS_HOME `pwd`</b>
% <b>mkdir bin classes lib src</b></source>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Source File">
	<p>One of the easier parts is the source itself for the
	  &#8216;null&#8217; profile handler.  Here it is:
	</p>
	<source>import java.util.Collections;
import java.util.List;
import jpl.eda.profile.Profile;
import jpl.eda.profile.handlers.ProfileHandler;
import jpl.eda.xmlquery.XMLQuery;

public class NullHandler implements ProfileHandler {
  public List findProfiles(XMLQuery query) {
    return Collections.EMPTY_LIST;
  }
  public Profile get(String id) {
    return null;
  }
}</source>

	<p>Note that for every query, the
	  <code>findProfiles</code> method returns an empty list
	  (meaning that no profiles matched), and that for any retrieval
	  the <code>get</code> method returns null, meaning that
	  the handler believes there's no such profile.
	</p>
	<p>This class should be compiled into a file named
	  <code>$PS_HOME/src/NullHandler.java</code>
	  since it is a public class.
	</p>

	<p><em>Note:</em> Profile handler classes <em>must</em> be
	  public <em>and</em> provide a no-arguments
	  constructor.  You should retrieve any initialization
	  settings through the System Properties or by other means
	  specific to your profile handler.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Compiling the Handler">
	<p>Compiling this profile handler requires the following
	  dependent components:
	</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><a href="/grid-profile/">Profile Service</a>.  This
	    defines the entire profile model, handler interfaces,
	    servers, clients, and so forth.
	  </li>
	  <li><a href="/edm-query/">Query Expression</a>.  This
	    defines the <code>XMLQuery</code> and related classes.
	  </li>
	</ul>

	<p>Download the binary distributions of the above two packages
	  and copy the jar file from each into the
	  <code>$PS_HOME/lib</code> directory.  Then you can compile
	  the <code>NullHandler.java</code> file.
	</p>

	<source>% <b>ls</b>
bin   classes   lib    src
% <b>ls -l lib</b>
total 244
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly   43879 28 Feb 07:05 edm-query-2.0.2.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  201453 28 Feb 07:01 grid-profile-3.0.2.jar
% <b>javac -extdirs lib -d classes src/NullHandler.java</b>
% <b>ls -l classes</b>
total 4
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  511 28 Feb 07:07 NullHandler.class
% <b>jar -cf lib/my-handler.jar -C classes NullHandler.class</b>
% <b>jar -tf lib/my-handler.jar</b>
META-INF/
META-INF/MANIFEST.MF
NullHandler.class</source>

	<p>We now have a new jar file, <code>my-handler.jar</code>
	  which contains our &#8216;null&#8217; profile handler,
	  compiled and ready to go.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Starting an RMI Registry">
	<p>Clients access profile servers with an open-ended set of
	  network protocols.  We currently have implementations for
	  RMI and CORBA.  For this tutorial, we'll use RMI, since it's
	  enormously less complex.  Clients of RMI systems first
	  contact an RMI registry and look up a server object's
	  network address.  The registry maintains mappings from a
	  server object's name to its network address.  When servers
	  start up, they register with the RMI registry so clients can
	  later find them.
	</p>

	<p>To start an RMI Registry, you'll need the following components:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><a href="/edm-commons/">EDM Common Components</a>.
	    These are common utilities used by every OODT
	    service.
	  </li>
	  <li><a href="/rmi-registry/">OODT RMI Registry</a>.  This is the
	    actual RMI registry.</li>
	</ul>

	<p>Download each component's binary distribution, unpack each
	  one, and take collect the jar files into the
	  <code>lib</code> directory.  The RMI Registry will also need
	  the <code>grid-profile</code> jar file, which we've already
	  got.
	</p>

	<source>% <b>ls -l $PS_HOME/lib</b>
total 404
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  149503 28 Feb 07:28 edm-commons-2.2.5.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly   43879 28 Feb 07:05 edm-query-2.0.2.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  201453 28 Feb 07:01 grid-profile-3.0.2.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly     796 28 Feb 07:07 my-handler.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly    8055 28 Feb 07:28 rmi-registry-1.0.0.jar</source>

	<p>Now all we need is a convenient script to start the RMI
	  registry.  We'll call it <code>rmi-reg</code> and stick it
	  in the <code>bin</code> directory.  Here's the
	  <code>rmi-reg</code> script:</p>

	<source>#!/bin/sh
exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
    gov.nasa.jpl.oodt.rmi.RMIRegistry</source>

	<p>This script tells the Java virtual machine to find
	  extension jars in the directory <code>$PS_HOME/lib</code>.  It
	  then says that the main class to execute is
	  <code>gov.nasa.jpl.oodt.rmi.RMIRegistry</code>.
	</p>

	<p>Go ahead and make this script executable and start the RMI
	  Registry. In another window (with the appropriate setting of
	  <code>PS_HOME</code>), run
	  <code>$PS_HOME/bin/rmi-reg</code>.  You should see output
	  similar to the following:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>chmod 755 $PS_HOME/bin/rmi-reg</b>
% <b>$PS_HOME/bin/rmi-reg</b>
Mon Feb 28 07:30:13 CST 2005: no objects registered</source>

	<p>The RMI Registry is now running.  Every two minutes it will
	  display an update of all registered objects.  Naturally, we
	  don't have any profile service running right now, so it will
	  say <code>no objects registered</code>.  Go ahead and ignore
	  this window for now.  It's time to start our profile server.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Starting the Profile Server">
	<p>With our handler compiled and our RMI registry running,
	  we're ready to start our profile server.  As said before,
	  profile servers delegate to zero or more profile handlers to
	  actually handle all incoming requests.  You tell the profile
	  server what handlers to instantiate by naming their classes
	  in a system property.  That property is called
	  <code>handlers</code>, and its value is a comma-separated
	  list of fully qualified class names, including the package
	  name prefixes.  Since our <code>NullHandler</code> is just
	  in the default package, <code>NullHandler</code> <em>is</em>
	  its fully-qualified class name.
	</p>

	<p>Profile server processes require the following components
	  in addition to the ones we've downloaded so far:</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><a href="http://ws.apache.org/xmlrpc">Apache
	      XML-RPC</a>.  This is used internally by OODT services.
	    Download version 1.1, not a later version!  If you prefer,
	    you can <a
	      href="http://ibiblio.org/maven/xmlrpc/jars/xmlrpc-1.1.jar">fetch
	      the jar file directly</a>.
	  </li>

	  <li><a href="http://jena.sourceforge.net/">Jena Semantic Web
	      Framework for Java</a>.  This is used by the classes
	      that represent profiles.  You'll need version 1.6.1 You
	      can also <a
	      href="http://oodt.jpl.nasa.gov/download/public/Jena/jars/jena-1.6.1.jar">fetch
	      the jar file directly</a>.
	  </li>
	</ul>

	<p>Copy these two other jars to the <code>$PS_HOME/lib</code>
	  directory.  You should now have seven jars there:
	</p>

	<source>% <b>ls -l $PS_HOME/lib</b>
total 1580
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly   149503 28 Feb 07:28 edm-commons-2.2.5.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly    43879 28 Feb 07:05 edm-query-2.0.2.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly   201453 28 Feb 07:01 grid-profile-3.0.2.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly  1144107 28 Feb 09:23 jena-1.6.1.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly      796 28 Feb 07:07 my-handler.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly     8055 28 Feb 07:28 rmi-registry-1.0.0.jar
-rw-r--r--  1 kelly  kelly    53978 28 Feb 09:20 xmlrpc-1.1.jar</source>

	<p>Now, create a second shell script to make starting the
	  profile server convenient and call it
	  <code>$PS_HOME/bin/ps</code>.  It should look like this:
	</p>

	<source>#!/bin/sh
exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
    -Dhandlers=NullHandler \
    jpl.eda.ExecServer \
    jpl.eda.profile.rmi.ProfileServiceImpl \
    urn:eda:rmi:MyProfileService</source>

	<p>Make the script executable and start the profile server:</p>

	<source>% <b>chmod 755 $PS_HOME/bin/ps</b>
% <b>$PS_HOME/bin/ps</b>
Object context ready; delegating to: [jpl.eda.object.jndi.RMIContext@dec8b3]</source>

	<p>The profile server will start, check its
	  <code>handlers</code> property, and create an object of each
	  class named by it.  Then it'll register itself with the RMI
	  registry and wait for requests to come in from profile clients.
	</p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="What's in a Name?">
	<p>The profile server registers itself using a name provided
	  on the command-line, in this case,
	  <code>urn:eda:rmi:MyProfileService</code>.  Let's take apart
	  the name and see how it works.
	</p>

	<p>If you're familiar with web standards, you can see that the
	  name is a Uniform Resource Name (URN), since it starts with
	  <code>urn:</code>.  The OODT Framework uses URNs to identify
	  services and other objects.  The <code>eda:</code> tells
	  that the name is part of the Enterprise Data Architecture
	  (EDA) namespace.  (EDA was the name of a project related to
	  OODT that was merged with OODT.  For now, just always use
	  <code>eda:</code> in your URNs.)
	</p>
	
	<p>Next comes <code>rmi:</code>.  This is a special flag for
	  the OODT services that tells that we're using a name of an
	  RMI-accessible object.  The OODT framework will know to use
	  an RMI registry to register the server. 
	</p>

	<p>Finally is <code>MyProfileService</code>.  This is the
	  actual name used in the RMI registry.  You can call your
	  profile server anything you want.  For example, suppose you
	  have three profile servers; one in the US, one in Canada,
	  and one in Australia.  You might name them:
	</p>

	<ul>
	  <li><code>urn:eda:rmi:US</code></li>
	  <li><code>urn:eda:rmi:Canada</code></li>
	  <li><code>urn:eda:rmi:Australia</code></li>
	</ul>

	<p>Or you might prefer to use ISO country codes.  Or you might
	  name them according to the kinds of profiles they serve,
	  such as <code>urn:eda:rmi:BiomarkerMetadata</code> or
	  <code>urn:eda:rmi:BusniessForecastMetadata</code>.
	</p>

	<p>The RMI registry will happily re-assign a name if one's
	  already in use, so when deploying your own profile (and
	  other) servers, be sure to give each one a unique name.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Querying the Profile Server">
	<p>To query a profile server, you use the
	  <code>ProfileClient</code> class.  It provides methods to
	  contact a named profile server, performing the lookup in the
	  RMI registry, contacting the profile server, and passing in
	  queries and profile retrievals.  The
	  <code>ProfileClient</code> class is also an
	  <em>executable</em> class, making it perfect for testing a
	  new profile server from the command-line.
	</p>

	<p>Still, we'll make a script, called
	  <code>$PS_HOME/bin/pc</code> (for "profile client") to
	  execute it, though, to save from having to type hugely long
	  Java command-lines:
	</p>

	<source>#!/bin/sh
if [ $# -ne 1 ]; then
   echo "Usage: `basename $0` &lt;query-expression&gt;" 1&gt;&amp;2
   exit 1
fi
exec java -Djava.ext.dirs=$PS_HOME/lib \
     jpl.eda.profile.ProfileClient \
     urn:eda:rmi:MyProfileService \
     "$1"</source>

	<p>Make this script executable and then run it:</p>

	<source>% <b>chmod 755 $PS_HOME/bin/pc</b>
% <b>$PS_HOME/bin/pc "temperature = 37"</b>
Object context ready; delegating to: [jpl.eda.object.jndi.RMIContext@dec8b3]
[]</source>

	<p>Although it may not look spetacular, this is a success!
	  The two square brackets, <code>[]</code>, indicates the list
	  of matching profiles to our query expression,
	  <code>temperature = 37</code>.  In this case, there were no
	  matches, which is exactly what we wanted.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section name="Conclusion">
      <p>The Null Profile Server made sure our development
	environment worked from end to end for creating, deploying, and
	testing a profile handler.  Now you're ready to implement a real
	profile handler:
      </p>

      <ul>
	<li>Instead of returning an empty list, create a
	    <code>Profile</code> object and return it as a
	    singleton list.  See the API documentation for
	    <code>Profile</code> as well as other articles
	    for manipulating this class.
	</li>
	<li>Analyze the methods of the
	  <code>XMLQuery</code> class to determine the
	  query passed in from the user.  Use that information to
	  synthesize the correct <code>Profile</code>
	  object.  See the API documentation for class
	  <code>XMLQuery</code> for more information.
	</li>
	<li>Connecting to an external data source (such as the
	    local filesystem or a database), synthesize appropriate
	  profiles in response to queries and profile retrieval with
	  the <code>get</code> method.
	</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
