<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Querying Profile Elements</title>
    <author email="Sean.Kelly@jpl.nasa.gov">Sean Kelly</author>
  </properties>
  <!-- Four Carry Nuts - Hexagon -->
  <body>
    <section name="Querying Profile Elements">

      <p>As desribed in <a href="../info/">Information Captured in a
	Profile</a>, profile elements describe the composition of a
	resource using metadata descriptions taken from the <a
	href="http://metadata-standards.org/11179/">ISO/IEC 11179
	standards</a>.  The profile elements catalog lists of valid
	values, minimum and maximum values, data types, and so forth.
      </p>

      <p>As you develop a profile handler to perform queries and
	generate profiles, you'll encounter three cases when querying
	profile elements or the data sources they describe:
      </p>

      <ul>
	<li>Querying ranges of values</li>
	<li>Querying enumerated values</li>
	<li>Querying unspecified profile lements</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="Queries Against Ranges">
      <p>Ranged profile elements are those that describe an attribute
	of a resource's composition in terms of a continuous space of
	valid values.  In the Java implementation, there's a subclass
	of <code>ProfileElement</code> to represent such ranges:
	<code>RangedProfileElement</code>.  In the XML representation,
	the <code>&lt;elemEnumFlag&gt;</code> is <code>F</code> and
	there are values listed for <code>&lt;elemMinValue&gt;</code>
	and <code>&lt;elemMaxValue&gt;</code>.
      </p>

      <p>An example of a ranged profile element might be:</p>
      <table>
	<tbody>
	  <tr><td>Name:</td><td>temperature</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Description:</td><td>Temperatures measured using
	  oral, medical-use, alcohol-based thermometer.</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Type:</td><td>real</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Unit:</td><td>kelvin</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Enumeration flag:</td><td>false</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Min value:</td><td>282.31</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Max value:</td><td>301.45</td></tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>

      <p>When you're generating a profile (or querying a similar
	metadata model) with a ranged element, queries should match if
	the sought value occurs within the given, inclusive range.  If
	it's a negative query, then it should match if the sought
	value <em>doesn't</em> occur within the range.
      </p>

      <p>Here's an example.  Suppose you have a ranged profile element
	called <code>lumens</code> and its minimum value is 10 and its
	maximum value is 20.  Here's a table that shows queries and
	whether they match:
      </p>

      <table>
	<thead>
	  <tr><th>Query</th><th>Match?</th></tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr><td>lumens = 12</td><td>Yes, since 12 is between 10 and 20</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens = 45</td><td>No, since 45 is above 20</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens != 12</td><td>Yes, since there are <em>other values</em> in the range 10..20 that match, such as 13, 14, 12.1, etc.</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens != 45</td><td>Yes, since are an infinite number of values in the range 10..22 that are not 45</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens != 10</td><td>Yes</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens &lt; 45</td><td>Yes</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens &gt; 15</td><td>Yes</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens &gt; 35</td><td>No; the highest lumen value is 20</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>lumens LIKE 12</td><td>Maybe</td></tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>

      <p>The "LIKE" relational operator defined by the XMLQuery query
	langauge was meant for string comparisons, yet there's nothing
	in the software that prevents it from being presented for
	ranged queries.  The choice of whether to match it is up to you.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Queries Against Enumerated Values">
      <p>Enumerated profile elements are those that describe an
	attribute of a resource's composition in terms of a discrete
	list of valid values.  In the Java implementation, there's a
	subclass of <code>ProfileElement</code> to represent such
	ranges: <code>EnumeratedProfileElement</code>.  In the XML
	representation, the <code>&lt;elemEnumFlag&gt;</code> is
	<code>T</code> and there are one or more
	<code>&lt;elemValue&gt;</code> elements.
      </p>

      <p>An example of an enumerated profile element might be:</p>
      <table>
	<tbody>
	  <tr><td>Name:</td><td>zone</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Description:</td><td>City Planning Commission zoning code for permitted land use.</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Type:</td><td>string</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Unit:</td><td>code</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Enumeration flag:</td><td>true</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>A</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>B1</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>B2</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>B4</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>C</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>H</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>PDD</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>R2</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>R3</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>R4</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>Value:</td><td>R5</td></tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>

      <p>When you're generating a profile (or querying a similar
	metadata model) with an enumerated element, queries should
	match if the sought value appears as one of the listed
	elements.
      </p>

      <p>Here's an example.  Suppose you have an profile element
	called <code>planet</code> that has as valid values
	<code>Mercury</code>, <code>Venus</code>, <code>Earth</code>,
	and <code>Mars</code>.  Here's a table that shows queries and
	whether they match:
      </p>

      <table>
	<thead>
	  <tr><th>Query</th><th>Match?</th></tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <tr><td>planet = Mercury</td><td>Yes</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>planet = Jupiter</td><td>No</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>planet != Mercury</td><td>Yes since Earth, Venus, and Mars are all not Mercury</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>planet != Jupiter</td><td>Yes since there are 4 planets which are all not Jupiter</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>planet &lt; Earth</td><td>Maybe</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>planet LIKE %E%</td><td>Yes, since all four planets have an E in them (without regard to case)</td></tr>
	  <tr><td>planet NOTLIKE %E%</td><td>No, since all four planets have an E in them</td></tr>
	</tbody>
      </table>

      <p>Relational ordering is not specified by the profile model, so whether
	a query like <code>planet &lt; Earth</code> matches is up to you.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Querying Against Unspecified Values">
      <p>An unspecific profile element indicates only the
	<em>presence</em> of an attribute in the composition of a
	resource, and nothing else.  In the Java implementation,
	there's a subclass of <code>ProfileElement</code> to represent
	this, <code>UnspecifiedProfileElement</code>.  In the XML
	representation, the <code>&lt;elemEnumFlag&gt;</code> is
	<code>T</code> and there are zero
	<code>&lt;elemValue&gt;</code> elements.
      </p>

      <p>Unspecified profile elements can be useful where you have
	profiles not describing single resources, but entire
	collections of resources.  For example, you may have ranged
	profile elements called <code>temperature</code> for each
	temperature resource.  But if there are a billion resources,
	then determining the minimum and maximum temperature for the
	profile of the entire collection might be painful, in which
	case you can say that the collection has a
	<code>temperature</code> attribute by using an unspecified
	profile for the element for the collection.
      </p>

      <p>Queries against unspecified elements always match, regardless
	what the query is.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
